A Guide to the Jane Hall Johnson Papers 1055-1986
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Jane Hall Johnson Papers 1955-1986
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
MS 2000-051
This collection consists of about 80 items.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Jane Hall Johnson were donated to Special Collections at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University by Jane Hall Johnson, via Deborah Rice, her niece in June 2001.
Biographical/Historical Information
Jane Hall was born in Maryville Missouri on October 11, 1911. She was the second of three daughters born to her parents, who were both school teachers. Shortly after her birth the family moved to St. Louis where Jane attended elementary and high school. In 1941, Hall graduated from the Missouri School of Mines with a degree in Civil Engineering. After graduation Hall worked at numerous firms as a structural engineer on highway design and airplane stress analysis. In 1949 Hall decided to go back to school to study architecture and graduated in 1955 with a Bachelor in Architecture, from Harvard University. In 1970 this degree was changed to a Master of Architecture.
From 1955-59 Hall worked in Boston as an architect for several firms, generally on working drawings and drafting, before moving back to St. Louis. On October 11, 1969, she married Benjamin Johnson and in 1970 they opened their own firm in St. Louis. Some of their larger clients included: the St. Louis Redevelopment Authority, the Human Development Corporation, Montgomery Hyde-Park, Johnson also completed numerous residences in the St. Louis area. Johnson enjoyed photographing her own projects.
Jane Hall Johnson retired in 1997.
Scope and Content Information
Drawings, blueprints, photographs of Jane Hall Johnson's architectural projects.
Arrangement
Oversized Folders 1-2 and Small folders 1-3: EDUCATION, 1955 This series contains drawings, presentation boards, photographs of models, slides, negatives of work for Johnson's Thesis, an International Student Center. Also included is a drawing of a separate grad school project-a Small Residence. The series is organized by material.
Oversized folders and Small folders: CREDENTIALS, 1958-94 Johnson's diploma from Harvard, her state registration certificates, and continuing education certificates.
Oversized folders: PROFESSIONAL WORK, 1956-86 Blueprints, drawings, and sketches of projects Johnson worked on while working for two firms, Anderson Nichols & Co, and Kilham, Hopkins, Greeley & Brodie after graduation. Preliminary drawings, sketches, construction drawings, presentation boards, for projects completed by Johnson's own firm. Materials are organized by date, then by project then by drawing type. Different projects are grouped together if they are the same type of drawing. There are a few drawings that have no noted firm affiliation, or date, but were done early in Johnson's career. These materials are organized under Miscellaneous Projects. Also included are Johnson's firm brochures, business correspondence.
Contents List
- Education 1955
  - Thesis-An International Student Center For the Greater Boston Area
    - Presentation Boards, 1 oversize folder
    - Photo book of models, 1 folder
    - Interior Drawings, 1 oversize folder
    - Thesis program, 1 folder
  - Graduate School Project-A Small Residence
    - Drawings, 1 oversize folder
  - Photo book of models for miscellaneous projects, 1 small folder
  - Photos, slides, and negatives of graduate projects, 2 small folders
- Credentials 1958-94
  - Harvard Diploma 1958, 1 oversize folder
  - State Registration Certificates 1961-1994, 1 small folder
  - Membership certificate: Society of American Registered Architects 1964, 1 folder
  - Continuing Education Certificates 1967, 1971, 1small folder
  - Certificate from Harvard changing Johnson's degree to a Masters 1970, 1 small folder
- Professional Work 1956-86
  - Anderson-Nichols & Co 1955-61
    - Drawings 1955-56
      - Raynham Elementary School
      - Sharon High School
    - Blueprints 1956-61
      - University of Missouri, Student Annex
      - Building connecting vocational recreational building and proposed treatment building
      - Laclede Gas Company, Meter Storage Building
      - Raynham Elementary School
    - Laclede Steel, Interior rooms n.d.
      - Sketches
    - Laclede Steel n.d.
      - Presentation Boards
  - Jamieson Spearl Hammond & Grolock Architects 1961
    - Wood River Township Hospital interior room sketches 1961, I small folder
  - Kilaham, Hopkins, Greeley 1957-61
    - Drawings
      - Franklin School
      - Cushing Academy
      - Central Junior High
      - Blytheswood
    - Blueprints 1961-62, n.d.
      - Cook Middle School n.d.
      - Minut-Shop Stores Inc. 1961
      - Renovation Caroline Mission 1962
    - Jane Hall Johnson 1973-1986
      - Firm Brochures, five 1973-81, 1 small folder
      - Business Correspondence 1973-76, 1 small folder
      - Proposal write-ups for firm brochures 1986, 1 small folder
    - B.P.O Elks Lodge 1973
      Presentation Boards
    - Retirement Village, Cuba Missouri 1973
    - Montgomery Hyde Park Health Clinic 1973, 2 folders
    - HDC Single Family Residence 1974
      Drawings
    - Schaller Residence, Prototype Single Family Residence 1974, 1979
      - Preliminary Drawings
      - Presentation Boards
    - HDC Retirement Village 1975-76
      - Preliminary Drawings 1975
      - Drawings 1975
      - Drawings 1976
    - New City Place 1976
    - Antoine Residence 1976-82
      - Preliminary Sketches 1976
      - Preliminary Drawings 1976, 2 folders
      - Drawings 1976-82
      - Construction Drawings 1976-78
      - Presentation Boards 1976-78, 2 folders
      - Interior Photos, 7 1986, 1 small folder
    - Williams Residence Addition, Walnut Park Senior Citizens Home, Fairfax Senior Citizens Home-Ramp 1977-79
      Construction Drawings
    - Q-Pit 1978
      - Drawings
    - Remodeling for Clarice Murphy 1978
      - Construction Drawings
    - Towne Furniture, Behlman Residence, Royal Vagabonds Tennis Courts and Swimming Pool 1978-79
      - Preliminary Drawings
    - Schaller Residence 1979
      - Construction Drawings
    - Herdlick Residence 1979
      - Construction Drawings
    - Rite Hall, Grand Haven Senior Citizens Center 1979
      - Preliminary Drawings
    - Benton Pride Senior, Carondelet, Montgomery Hyde Park Senior Citizens Home 1980
      - Construction Drawings
    - HDC Retirement Village 1980
      - Presentation Boards
    - Parent Child center 1981
      - Schematic Design
      - Construction Drawings
      - Drawings
    - Wellston Municipal Building, unidentified Residence 1981
      - Preliminary Drawings
    - Shop Plaza News 1982
      - Preliminary Drawings
    - Jockerst Residence 1982
      - Preliminary Drawings
    - Frank's Tower 1982
      - Preliminary Drawings
    - Sun Crest Senior Citizens Housing 1982
      - Preliminary Drawings
    - Case Residence 1983-85
      - Construction Drawings 1983
      - Presentation Boards 1984-85
    - NRG Saves Inc/Energy Savings Shop 1983
      - Drawings
    - CMC Medical Buildings, Credit Systems Cafeteria Patio 1983-84
      - Preliminary Drawings
    - Daniels Residence 1984
      - Construction Drawings
    - Grand View Heights 1984-85
      - Presentation Boards
    - Vlasaty Residence, Brandav Residence 1985
      - Construction Drawings
    - Melone Addition, Places for People, Stair Addition 1985
      - Construction Drawings
    - Two Town houses 1986
      - Preliminary Drawings
    - Frimel Addition 1986
      - Drawings
    - Kennerly Temple Apartments n.d.
      - Presentation Boards
      - Drawings
  - Miscellaneous Projects
    - Daniel and Henry n.d
      - Lobby Sketches, 1 small folder
    - American Insurance Company n.d.
      - Handrail scheme sketches, 1 small folder
      - Lobby scheme sketches, 1 small folder
    - Unidentified Project n.d.
      - Lounge and Patio sketches, 1 small folder
    - Materials for unidentified project n.d
    - Painting n.d.